Simon Fraser University Faculty Association fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
Simon Fraser University Faculty Association fonds
1963 - 1991
F-79
Q106642968
3 m of textual records 1 sound recording
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
PHYSICAL DESCRIPTION Fonds includes 1 sound recording (item F-79-6-8-0-16-1) of a grievance hearing, original on audio tape, backup copy subsequently made by the Archives on audio cassette.
Simon Fraser University Faculty Association
The Simon Fraser University Faculty Association was incorporated under the British Columbia Societies Act on June 24, 1969, although it had been active on campus since the university opened in 1965. The Association is concerned with the economic benefits available to faculty including salary and fringe benefits; grievances; conditions of employment; procedural matters with respect to promotion, granting of tenure, dismissal and disciplinary actions; and other related areas. The Faculty Association also concerns itself with asserting the integrity of the academic profession, defending independence of thought, and encouraging the social and recreational association of its members.
On the Provincial level, the Association is a charter member of the Confederation of University Faculty Associations of British Columbia (CUFABC) and is a member of the governing council. Nationally, the Simon Fraser University Faculty Association is a member of the Canadian Association of University Teachers (CAUT).
An Executive Council elected by the membership administers the Faculty Association. The Executive consists of the President, Vice President, and Directors. In 1969, there were six Directors, which increased to eight by 1998. See Appendix A8 for a list of Executive Committee members from 1965 to 1988. Over the years various standing and ad hoc committees have assisted the Executive Council. The most recent constitution (1998) provides for an Economic Benefits Committee and a Pension Committee.
Currently, the Faculty Association continues to advocate on behalf of its members, and acts as their representative in the faculty's relationship with the university.
published
Full
Revised
Title is based on the name of the organization.
The fonds consist of records created, received, and collected by the Simon Fraser University Faculty Association in carrying out its functional activities. Includes records relating to its Constitution and by-laws, policy development, correspondence, general and special meetings, the executive committee, standing and ad hoc committees, and publications.
The materials were arranged by the Archivist.
Sound recordings; Textual records; Labour
The fonds was donated by the Simon Fraser Faculty Association in several accessions.
All accessions have been processed as of September 2002. Further accruals are expected.
See also inventories of the Faculty Council F-112, the Joint Faculty F-113, and the Simon Fraser University Faculty Women's Association F-78.
Some files may contain personal or confidential information. Access to these files may be restricted as stipulated by Archives policy or the donor. Files marked 'pending review' must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release, and as a result of the review access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
Series descriptions and file lists are available.
- Constitution and by-laws, 1967 - 1976; F-79-1; 4 cm of textual records
  published
  Series consists of the constitution and by-laws of the Simon Fraser University Faculty Association. Includes the Certificate of Incorporation, memoranda of understanding, a list of Faculty Association presidents, proposed revisions to the constitution and correspondence.
  - Societies Act, 1969 - 1972; F-79-1-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 79-1)
    Textual records
    Pending review
  - By-Laws and Correspondence, 1967 - 1976; F-79-1-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 79-1)
  - SFU Faculty Association Constitution, 1970 - 1974; F-79-1-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 79-1)
- University policy development, 1966 - 1980; F-79-2; 8 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to the development of policies and procedures for a wide range of topics of concern to the Faculty Association including student participation in departmental affairs, liquor control, copyright, resignations, dismissals of faculty, and sabbatical leaves. Includes correspondence, briefs, reports of interim councils, memoranda of understanding, draft policies, and approved policies.
  - Policies and Procedures - University Government, 1966 - 1969; F-79-2-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 79-1)
  - Policies and Procedures I - General, 1968 - 1980; F-79-2-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 79-1)
  - Policies and Procedures II - Dismissals, 1974; F-79-2-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 79-1)
  - Policies and Procedures II - Dismissals Correspondence, 1969 - 1974; F-79-2-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 79-1)
    Open
  - Policies and Procedures II - Dismissals Memoranda, 1968 - 1973; F-79-2-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 79-1)
  - Policies and Procedures - Sabbatical and leave, 1970 - 1974; F-79-2-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 79-1)
- Correspondence, 1965 - 1985; F-79-3; 75 cm of textual records
  Series consists of correspondence and related records of the Simon Fraser Faculty Association. Includes records that reflect the day to day activities of the Faculty Association as well as specific issues, such as the PSA Strike. Includes external and internal correspondence and copies of memoranda from the Canadian Association of University Teachers (CAUT).
  Canadian Association of University Teachers
  - General, 1965 - 1985; F-79-3-1; 53 cm of textual records
    Sub-series consists of general internal and external correspondence on a wide range of topics and issues.
    - Correspondence - general, 1965 - 1967; F-79-3-1-0-1 (Archival box - standard 79-2)
    - Correspondence - general, 1968; F-79-3-1-0-2 (Archival box - standard 79-2)
    - Correspondence - general, 1968; F-79-3-1-0-3 (Archival box - standard 79-2)
    - Correspondence - general, 1969; F-79-3-1-0-4 (Archival box - standard 79-2)
      Restricted in whole
    - Correspondence - general, 1969; F-79-3-1-0-5 (Archival box - standard 79-2)
    - Correspondence - general, 1970 - 1973; F-79-3-1-0-6 (Archival box - standard 79-2)
    - Correspondence - external, 1970; F-79-3-1-0-7 (Archival box - standard 79-3)
    - Correspondence - internal, 1970; F-79-3-1-0-8 (Archival box - standard 79-3)
    - Correspondence - external, 1971; F-79-3-1-0-9 (Archival box - standard 79-3)
    - Correspondence - internal, 1971; F-79-3-1-0-10 (Archival box - standard 79-3)
    - Correspondence - external, 1972; F-79-3-1-0-11 (Archival box - standard 79-3)
    - Correspondence - internal, 1972; F-79-3-1-0-12 (Archival box - standard 79-3)
    - Correspondence - external, 1973; F-79-3-1-0-13 (Archival box - standard 79-3)
    - Correspondence - internal, 1973; F-79-3-1-0-14 (Archival box - standard 79-3)
    - Correspondence - general, 1974 - 1975; F-79-3-1-0-15 (Archival box - standard 79-3)
    - Correspondence - external, 1974; F-79-3-1-0-16 (Archival box - standard 79-3)
    - Correspondence - internal (2 files), 1974; F-79-3-1-0-17.1 (Archival box - standard 79-3)
    - Correspondence - internal (2 files), 1974; F-79-3-1-0-17.2 (Archival box - standard 79-4)
      Restricted in part
    - Correspondence - miscellaneous, 1975 - 1976; F-79-3-1-0-18 (Archival box - standard 79-4)
    - Correspondence - general, 1976 - 1979; F-79-3-1-0-19 (Archival box - standard 79-4)
    - Correspondence - general, 1978; F-79-3-1-0-20 (Archival box - standard 79-4)
    - Correspondence - with Administration and Board, 1978 - 1980; F-79-3-1-0-21 (Archival box - standard 79-4)
    - Correspondence - external, 1978 - 1980; F-79-3-1-0-22 (Archival box - standard 79-4)
    - Correspondence - internal, 1978 - 1980; F-79-3-1-0-23 (Archival box - standard 79-4)
    - Correspondence - general, 1980; F-79-3-1-0-24 (Archival box - standard 79-4)
    - Correspondence - internal received, 1971 - 1980; F-79-3-1-0-25 (Archival box - standard 79-5)
    - Correspondence - general, 1981; F-79-3-1-0-26 (Archival box - standard 79-5)
    - Correspondence - general, 1982; F-79-3-1-0-27 (Archival box - standard 79-5)
    - Correspondence - general, 1982; F-79-3-1-0-28 (Archival box - standard 79-5)
    - Correspondence - general, 1983; F-79-3-1-0-29 (Archival box - standard 79-5)
    - Correspondence - general, 1983; F-79-3-1-0-30 (Archival box - standard 79-5)
    - Correspondence - general, 1984; F-79-3-1-0-31 (Archival box - standard 79-6)
    - Correspondence - general, 1985; F-79-3-1-0-32 (Archival box - standard 79-6)
  - Departmental, 1966 - 1983; F-79-3-2; 6 cm of textual records
    Sub-series consists of correspondence between the Faculty Association and SFU departments, including PSA, Chemistry, English and others.
    Department of Political Science, Sociology and Anthropology; Department of English; Department of Chemistry
    - Correspondence - departmental, 1966 - 1967; F-79-3-2-0-1 (Archival box - standard 79-6)
    - Correspondence - departmental, 1968; F-79-3-2-0-2 (Archival box - standard 79-6)
    - Correspondence - departmental, 1969 - 1974; F-79-3-2-0-3 (Archival box - standard 79-6)
    - Correspondence - departmental, 1981 - 1983; F-79-3-2-0-4 (Archival box - standard 79-6)
  - Subject, 1968 - 1975; F-79-3-3; 4 cm of textual records
    Sub-series consists of correspondence relating to specific subjects, such as the 12 Hour week, and others.
    - Correspondence - 12 Hours Week - Jewett, 1971 - 1975; F-79-3-3-0-1 (Archival box - standard 79-6)
      Jewett, Pauline; Textual records
    - Correspondence - re: John Matthews Affair, 1968 - 1970; F-79-3-3-0-2 (Archival box - standard 79-6)
      Mathews, John; Textual records
    - Correspondence - re: censure, 1970 - 1975; F-79-3-3-0-3 (Archival box - standard 79-6)
  - Canadian Association of University Teachers (CAUT), 1967 - 1976; F-79-3-4; 13 cm of textual records
    Sub-series consists of correspondence generated by the Canadian Association of University Teachers (CAUT) on a range of topics, including the censure of SFU, women's rights, disaffiliation from the CAUT and others.
    - CAUT censure of SFU, 1967 - 1969; F-79-3-4-0-1 (Archival box - standard 79-7)
    - CAUT censure of SFU, 1970 - 1971; F-79-3-4-0-2 (Archival box - standard 79-7)
    - Disaffiliation from CAUT, 1972 - 1973; F-79-3-4-0-3 (Archival box - standard 79-7)
    - CAUT - Memoranda, 1967 - 1974; F-79-3-4-0-4 (Archival box - standard 79-7)
    - CAUT - Memoranda, 1975 - 1976; F-79-3-4-0-5 (Archival box - standard 79-7)
    - Women's Rights, 1971 - 1974; F-79-3-4-0-6 (Archival box - standard 79-7)
    - CAUT - general, 1970 - 1974; F-79-3-4-0-7 (Archival box - standard 79-7)
- General and Special Meetings, 1966 - 1987; F-79-4; 15 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to annual general meetings and special meetings of the Simon Fraser University Faculty Association. Records reflect general business of the Faculty Association as well as consideration of special issues. Includes agendas, minutes, correspondence, notices and reports.
  - General Meetings, 1966 - 1969; F-79-4-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 79-8)
  - Special Meetings, 1967 - 1973; F-79-4-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 79-8)
  - Annual General Meetings, 1967 - 1987; F-79-4-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 79-8)
  - General Meetings, 1970 - 1986; F-79-4-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 79-8)
  - General and Special Meetings, 1970; F-79-4-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 79-8)
  - General and Special Meetings, 1971; F-79-4-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 79-8)
  - General and Special Meetings, 1972; F-79-4-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 79-8)
  - General and Special Meetings, 1973; F-79-4-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 79-8)
  - General and Special Meetings 1/2, 1974; F-79-4-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 79-8)
  - General and Special Meetings 2/2, 1974; F-79-4-0-0-9.1 (Archival box - standard 79-9)
  - General and Special Meetings, 1975; F-79-4-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 79-9)
- Executive Committee, 1965 - 1990; F-79-5; 37 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records of the Faculty Association's Executive Committee. Records reflect a wide range of issues affecting the faculty at Simon Fraser University as well as more routine matters. Includes directories, financial statements, agenda and minutes of committee meetings, correspondence, and sub-committee reports.
  - Executive Committee: Membership lists, 1971 - 1990; F-79-5-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 79-9)
  - Executive Committee - Treasury, 1970 - 1974; F-79-5-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 79-9)
  - Executive Committee, 1965 - 1967; F-79-5-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 79-9)
  - Executive Committee, 1968; F-79-5-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 79-9)
  - Executive Committee, 1969; F-79-5-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 79-9)
  - Executive Committee, 1970; F-79-5-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 79-9)
  - Executive Committee, 1971; F-79-5-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 79-9)
  - Executive Committee, 1972 - 1973; F-79-5-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 79-9)
  - Executive Committee, 1974; F-79-5-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 79-10)
  - Executive Committee, 1975; F-79-5-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 79-10)
  - Executive Committee, 1976; F-79-5-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 79-10)
  - Executive Committee, 1977; F-79-5-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 79-10)
  - Executive Committee, 1978; F-79-5-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 79-10)
  - Executive Committee, 1979; F-79-5-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 79-10)
  - Executive Committee, 1980; F-79-5-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 79-10)
  - Executive Committee, 1981; F-79-5-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 79-10)
  - Executive Committee, 1982; F-79-5-0-0-17 (Archival box - standard 79-10)
  - Executive Committee, 1982; F-79-5-0-0-18 (Archival box - standard 79-11)
  - Executive Committee, 1983; F-79-5-0-0-19 (Archival box - standard 79-11)
  - Executive Committee, 1984; F-79-5-0-0-20 (Archival box - standard 79-11)
  - Executive Committee: Cafeteria Sub-Committee, 1969 - 1970; F-79-5-0-0-21 (Archival box - standard 79-11)
  - Executive Committee minutes, 1970; F-79-5-0-0-22 (Archival box - standard 79-11)
  - Executive Committee minutes, 1971; F-79-5-0-0-23 (Archival box - standard 79-11)
  - Executive Committee minutes, 1972; F-79-5-0-0-24 (Archival box - standard 79-11)
  - Executive Committee minutes, 1973; F-79-5-0-0-25 (Archival box - standard 79-11)
  - Executive Committee minutes, 1974; F-79-5-0-0-26 (Archival box - standard 79-11)
  - Executive Committee minutes, 1980; F-79-5-0-0-27 (Archival box - standard 79-12)
- Standing and Ad Hoc Committees, 1963 - 1985; F-79-6; 1.49 m of textual records
  Series consists of records of standing and ad hoc committees of the Simon Fraser University Faculty Association. Includes correspondence, policy statements, reports, briefs, articles, agenda, constitution, by-laws, proposals, financial statements, and architectural plans.
  - Academic Freedom and Tenure Committee, 1966 - 1974; F-79-6-1; 16 cm of textual records
    Sub-series consists of records of the Academic Freedom and Tenure Committee. Activities documented include the development of a statement and policy on academic freedom and tenure at Simon Fraser University. Includes correspondence, policy statements, reports, briefs, and articles.
    - Academic Freedom and Tenure Committee, 1966 - 1967; F-79-6-1-0-1 (Archival box - standard 79-12)
    - Academic Freedom and Tenure Committee, 1968; F-79-6-1-0-2 (Archival box - standard 79-12)
    - Academic Freedom and Tenure Committee, 1969 - 1970; F-79-6-1-0-3 (Archival box - standard 79-12)
    - Academic Freedom and Tenure Committee, 1970; F-79-6-1-0-4 (Archival box - standard 79-12)
    - Academic Freedom and Tenure Committee, 1970 - 1974; F-79-6-1-0-5 (Archival box - standard 79-12)
    - Academic Freedom and Tenure Committee, 1971; F-79-6-1-0-6 (Archival box - standard 79-12)
    - Academic Freedom and Tenure Committee, 1971 - 1972; F-79-6-1-0-7 (Archival box - standard 79-13)
    - Academic Freedom and Tenure Committee, 1972; F-79-6-1-0-8 (Archival box - standard 79-13)
    - Academic Freedom and Tenure Committee, 1973; F-79-6-1-0-9 (Archival box - standard 79-13)
  - Collective Bargaining Committee, 1976 - 1977; F-79-6-2; 2 cm of textual records
    Sub-series consists of records of the Collective Bargaining Committee. Activities documented are the Faculty Association's steps to achieve recognition as the collective bargaining agent for all those eligible for membership in the Association, and its actions as that body. Includes agenda, correspondence, articles, and the 1977 report of the Committee.
    - Collective Bargaining Committee, 1976 - 1977; F-79-6-2-0-1 (Archival box - standard 79-13)
  - Economic Benefits Committee, 1972 - 1985; F-79-6-3; 5 cm of textual records
    Sub-series consists of records of the Economic Benefits Committee. Activities documented are advocacy for employee benefits such as salary increases, disability benefits, and insurance. Includes correspondence, memoranda, and reports.
    - Economic Benefits Committee, 1972; F-79-6-3-0-1 (Archival box - standard 79-13)
    - Economic Benefits Committee, 1974 - 1979; F-79-6-3-0-2 (Archival box - standard 79-13)
    - Economic Benefits Committee, 1979 - 1985; F-79-6-3-0-3 (Archival box - standard 79-13)
  - Faculty Club Committee, 1967 - 1982; F-79-6-4; 11 cm of textual records
    Sub-series consists of records of the Faculty Club Committee. Activities documented are efforts to provide, maintain and operate a centre for the recreation and convenience of faculty members and the University community. Includes the constitution and by-laws of the faculty club, minutes, reports, architectural assessments, proposals, transparencies, financial statements, and correspondence.
    - Faculty Club Committee: Constitution and By-Laws, 1970 - 1972; F-79-6-4-0-1 (Archival box - standard 79-13)
    - Faculty Club Committee: Agenda and Minutes, 1969 - 1972; F-79-6-4-0-2 (Archival box - standard 79-14)
    - Faculty Club Committee: Correspondence, 1967 - 1969; F-79-6-4-0-3 (Archival box - standard 79-14)
    - Faculty Club Committee: Correspondence, 1970; F-79-6-4-0-4 (Archival box - standard 79-14)
    - Faculty Club Committee: Correspondence, 1970 - 1974; F-79-6-4-0-5 (Archival box - standard 79-14)
    - Faculty Club Committee: Correspondence, 1971; F-79-6-4-0-6 (Archival box - standard 79-14)
    - Faculty Club Committee: Correspondence, 1972; F-79-6-4-0-7 (Archival box - standard 79-14)
    - Faculty Club Committee: Correspondence, 1976 - 1982; F-79-6-4-0-8 (Archival box - standard 79-14)
  - Ad Hoc Committees, 1966 - 1974; F-79-6-5; 6 cm of textual records
    Sub-series consists of records of committees set up to deal with Master Teacher awards, liaison, and University development. Includes memoranda, proposals, correspondence, and minutes.
    - Ad Hoc Committee on Master Teacher Awards: Terms of Reference, 1973; F-79-6-5-0-1 (Archival box - standard 79-14)
    - Ad Hoc Committee on Master Teacher Awards: Correspondence, 1972 - 1974; F-79-6-5-0-2 (Archival box - standard 79-14)
    - Ad Hoc Liaison Committee, 1967; F-79-6-5-0-3 (Archival box - standard 79-15)
    - Ad Hoc Committee on University Development, 1966; F-79-6-5-0-4 (Archival box - standard 79-15)
      Open, no restrictions
      Access review (Jan 31, 2023) – File is open, no restricted information identified.
  - Pension Committees, 1966 - 1981; F-79-6-6; 6 cm of textual records
    Sub-series consists of records of the Pension Committee. Activities documented include proposals and advocacy towards achieving a pension plan for SFU faculty and setting up an Advisory Committee. Includes correspondence, reports, terms of reference, and pension plans.
    - Pension Committee, 1966 - 1968; F-79-6-6-0-1 (Archival box - standard 79-15)
    - Pension Committee, 1969; F-79-6-6-0-2 (Archival box - standard 79-15)
    - Pension Committee, 1970 - 1974; F-79-6-6-0-3 (Archival box - standard 79-15)
    - Pension Committee, 1970 - 1981; F-79-6-6-0-4 (Archival box - standard 79-15)
  - Salaries and Negotiations Committee, 1966 - 1981; F-79-6-7; 33 cm of textual records
    Sub-series consists of records of the Salaries and Negotiations Committee. Activities document advocacy for comparable salaries with other universities, pay increments, merit and equity adjustments, and other negotiations regarding faculty salaries. Includes correspondence, memoranda, proposals, briefs, and reports.
    - Salaries and Negotiations Committee, 1966 - 1967; F-79-6-7-0-1 (Archival box - standard 79-15)
    - Salaries and Negotiations Committee, 1968; F-79-6-7-0-2 (Archival box - standard 79-15)
    - Salaries and Negotiations Committee, 1969 - 1971; F-79-6-7-0-3 (Archival box - standard 79-15)
    - Salaries and Negotiations Committee, 1970; F-79-6-7-0-4 (Archival box - standard 79-16)
    - Salaries and Negotiations Committee, 1971; F-79-6-7-0-5 (Archival box - standard 79-16)
    - Salaries and Negotiations Committee 1/3, 1972; F-79-6-7-0-6 (Archival box - standard 79-16)
    - Salaries and Negotiations Committee 2/3, 1972; F-79-6-7-0-7 (Archival box - standard 79-16)
    - Salaries and Negotiations Committee 3/3, 1972; F-79-6-7-0-7.1 (Archival box - standard 79-16)
    - Salaries and Negotiations Committee, 1973; F-79-6-7-0-8 (Archival box - standard 79-16)
    - Salaries and Negotiations Committee, 1973 - 1974; F-79-6-7-0-9 (Archival box - standard 79-17)
    - Salaries and Negotiations Committee, 1974; F-79-6-7-0-10 (Archival box - standard 79-17)
    - Salaries and Negotiations Committee, 1975 - 1976; F-79-6-7-0-11 (Archival box - standard 79-17)
    - Salaries and Negotiations Committee, 1976 - 1977; F-79-6-7-0-12 (Archival box - standard 79-17)
    - Salaries and Negotiations Committee, 1978 - 1980; F-79-6-7-0-13 (Archival box - standard 79-17)
    - Salaries and Negotiations Committee, 1981; F-79-6-7-0-14 (Archival box - standard 79-17)
    - Salaries and Negotiations Committee - Reports 1/2, 1967 - 1979; F-79-6-7-0-15 (Archival box - standard 79-18)
    - Salaries and Negotiations Committee - Reports 2/2, 1967 - 1979; F-79-6-7-0-16 (Archival box - standard 79-18)
    - Salaries and Negotiations Committee: Minutes, 1968 - 1977; F-79-6-7-0-17 (Archival box - standard 79-18)
  - University Affairs Committee, 1963 - 1981; F-79-6-8; 64 cm of textual records 1 sound recording
    Sub-series consists of records of the University Affairs Committee. Activities documented are the investigation and reporting of grievances by faculty, students and staff. Includes frames of reference, minutes, agendas, correspondence, policy statements, reports, and grievance investigation records for specific cases such as the PSA controversy and others.
    Department of Political Science, Sociology and Anthropology
    Some files may contain personal or confidential information. Access to these files may be restricted as stipulated by Archives policy or the donor. Files marked "pending review" must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release and, as a result of the review, access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
    - University Affairs Committee: Terms of Reference, 1969 - 1970; F-79-6-8-0-1 (Archival box - standard 79-18)
    - University Affairs Committee: Minutes, 1967 - 1969; F-79-6-8-0-2 (Archival box - standard 79-18)